If the mind still feels half-open tonight, stay here with me and let this be the moment you stop standing at the gate of the day.
If the day is still clinging to you a little, that is all right. We do not have to pull it away all at once.
Let this be quieter than a practice and more like company at the end of a long day.
There is nothing you need to prepare before rest is allowed to begin.
Feel the surface beneath you taking the weight of your head, your shoulders, your back, your hips, and your legs.
Feel the body resting as if the night air has finally reached you, and let each exhale be a small step through that gate into something simpler, quieter, and unforced.
Let the throat be easy. Let the chest stop bracing. Let the belly loosen the way it does when you finally know you are alone and safe.
The tiny muscles around the eyes can soften now. The jaw can soften. The tongue can rest.
You do not have to do this well tonight. You only have to let yourself be here.
You do not need a technique to impress anyone here. A soft breath is enough. A longer exhale is enough.
A restless night can still become a gentle one.
Let the body feel heavier in the kindest way, not sinking, only being received.
For now, nothing needs to be changed. Let this moment be exactly as it is, and let that be enough.
If it helps, think of the exhale as the part of the breath that knows the way home.
You are allowed to be tired without needing to explain why.
Each time the breath leaves, let the shoulders drop by the smallest amount, like a room dimming at night.
Even now, the body may be unwinding in ways you do not have to notice to benefit from.
It may help to imagine you are floating just below the surface of still water, held quietly from all sides.
You do not have to chase away thought. Simply notice it, and let it pass without following it anywhere.
Nothing has to become perfect. It only has to become slightly easier than it was a moment ago.
If some feeling is still awake inside you, let it be there without turning it into a problem.
If sleep comes before this recording ends, you do not need to keep me with you. You can leave my voice behind.
Take one unhurried breath in, and let the exhale be a little longer, as though the body is putting something down.
Nothing in you has to be solved before sleep can come closer.
The night does not need anything from you now except your willingness to be carried a little.
Let the next breath arrive on its own. You are not managing it. You are only meeting it.
If the mind is still talking, let it talk farther away. You do not need to answer it.
Sit inwardly with the night the way you might sit beside a quiet window, not asking for anything, only keeping company.
You do not need a technique to impress anyone here. A soft breath is enough. A longer exhale is enough.
A restless night can still become a gentle one.
Picture your thoughts drifting like distant lights seen from far away. They can remain there without reaching you.
If it helps, think of the exhale as the part of the breath that knows the way home.
You are allowed to be tired without needing to explain why.
You do not have to stay ahead of the night. You can let the night catch up to you.
Each time the breath leaves, let the shoulders drop by the smallest amount, like a room dimming at night.
Even now, the body may be unwinding in ways you do not have to notice to benefit from.
Picture your thoughts drifting like distant lights seen from far away. They can remain there without reaching you.
Awake or half asleep, you can remain simple here, breathing, resting, letting the mind widen instead of tighten.
Notice how the body may already be a little farther away from the day than when we began.
You do not need to check whether it is working. Checking wakes the mind back up. Let not knowing be part of the rest.
Nothing has to become perfect. It only has to become slightly easier than it was a moment ago.
If some feeling is still awake inside you, let it be there without turning it into a problem.
Take one unhurried breath in, and let the exhale be a little longer, as though the body is putting something down.
Nothing in you has to be solved before sleep can come closer.
Let the next breath arrive on its own. You are not managing it. You are only meeting it.
If the mind is still talking, let it talk farther away. You do not need to answer it.
You do not need a technique to impress anyone here. A soft breath is enough. A longer exhale is enough.
A restless night can still become a gentle one.
If it helps, think of the exhale as the part of the breath that knows the way home.
You are allowed to be tired without needing to explain why.
Each time the breath leaves, let the shoulders drop by the smallest amount, like a room dimming at night.
Even now, the body may be unwinding in ways you do not have to notice to benefit from.
Nothing has to become perfect. It only has to become slightly easier than it was a moment ago.
If some feeling is still awake inside you, let it be there without turning it into a problem.
You do not have to stay ahead of the night. You can let the night catch up to you.
Sometimes the first gift of the night is not sleep itself, but the moment the body stops arguing with wakefulness.
Now let the breaths become smaller, quieter, almost private.
If you notice my voice fading from your attention, that is a good thing. You can keep drifting.
If sleep is near, let it meet you like soft blossom air moving through a quiet orchard. If you are still awake, stay here a little longer and let the night keep opening.
Stay with the softness. Stay with the support beneath you. Let the rest of the night do the rest.