If the day has left a little weather inside you, stay here with me and let the night settle after the rain.
You do not have to do this well tonight. You only have to let yourself be here.
If the day is still clinging to you a little, that is all right. We do not have to pull it away all at once.
Let the throat be easy. Let the chest stop bracing. Let the belly loosen the way it does when you finally know you are alone and safe.
The tiny muscles around the eyes can soften now. The jaw can soften. The tongue can rest.
Feel the body being held in the quiet that comes after movement, and let each breath soften whatever is still trying to keep watch.
Feel the surface beneath you taking the weight of your head, your shoulders, your back, your hips, and your legs.
There is nothing you need to prepare before rest is allowed to begin.
For these next few minutes, you can stop holding yourself up in all the usual ways.
Take one unhurried breath in, and let the exhale be a little longer, as though the body is putting something down.
You are allowed to be tired without needing to explain why.
The night does not need anything from you now except your willingness to be carried a little.
For now, nothing needs to be changed. Let this moment be exactly as it is, and let that be enough.
You do not need a technique to impress anyone here. A soft breath is enough. A longer exhale is enough.
If the mind is still talking, let it talk farther away. You do not need to answer it.
Let the next breath arrive on its own. You are not managing it. You are only meeting it.
If some feeling is still awake inside you, let it be there without turning it into a problem.
Picture your thoughts drifting like distant lights seen from far away. They can remain there without reaching you.
You do not have to chase away thought. Simply notice it, and let it pass without following it anywhere.
Nothing has to become perfect. It only has to become slightly easier than it was a moment ago.
Even now, the body may be unwinding in ways you do not have to notice to benefit from.
If sleep comes before this recording ends, you do not need to keep me with you. You can leave my voice behind.
If it helps, think of the exhale as the part of the breath that knows the way home.
Nothing in you has to be solved before sleep can come closer.
Imagine the room growing softer around you, as though the night is folding a blanket over every sharp edge.
Each time the breath leaves, let the shoulders drop by the smallest amount, like a room dimming at night.
A restless night can still become a gentle one.
Sit inwardly with the night the way you might sit beside a quiet window, not asking for anything, only keeping company.
Take one unhurried breath in, and let the exhale be a little longer, as though the body is putting something down.
You are allowed to be tired without needing to explain why.
Let the body feel heavier in the kindest way, not sinking, only being received.
You do not need a technique to impress anyone here. A soft breath is enough. A longer exhale is enough.
If the mind is still talking, let it talk farther away. You do not need to answer it.
Let this be one of those quiet moments where nothing is demanded of you.
Notice how the body may already be a little farther away from the day than when we began.
You do not need to check whether it is working. Checking wakes the mind back up. Let not knowing be part of the rest.
Let the next breath arrive on its own. You are not managing it. You are only meeting it.
If some feeling is still awake inside you, let it be there without turning it into a problem.
Let the body feel heavier in the kindest way, not sinking, only being received.
Awake or half asleep, you can remain simple here, breathing, resting, letting the mind widen instead of tighten.
Nothing has to become perfect. It only has to become slightly easier than it was a moment ago.
Even now, the body may be unwinding in ways you do not have to notice to benefit from.
If it helps, think of the exhale as the part of the breath that knows the way home.
Nothing in you has to be solved before sleep can come closer.
Each time the breath leaves, let the shoulders drop by the smallest amount, like a room dimming at night.
A restless night can still become a gentle one.
Take one unhurried breath in, and let the exhale be a little longer, as though the body is putting something down.
You are allowed to be tired without needing to explain why.
Let this be one of those quiet moments where nothing is demanded of you.
And if you are not asleep yet, that does not mean this is failing. Rest often arrives in layers.
Now let the breaths become smaller, quieter, almost private.
If you notice my voice fading from your attention, that is a good thing. You can keep drifting.
If sleep is close now, let it come gently. If you are still awake, stay with the warmth a little longer and let the night finish the rest.
Stay with the softness. Stay with the support beneath you. Let the rest of the night do the rest.