If your mind is still moving tonight, stay here with me and let this be simpler than trying to sleep.
For these next few minutes, you can stop holding yourself up in all the usual ways.
If the day is still clinging to you a little, that is all right. We do not have to pull it away all at once.
There is nothing you need to prepare before rest is allowed to begin.
Let the throat be easy. Let the chest stop bracing. Let the belly loosen the way it does when you finally know you are alone and safe.
Feel the body being held where it is, and let each breath loosen the habit of following every thought that passes by.
The tiny muscles around the eyes can soften now. The jaw can soften. The tongue can rest.
Feel the surface beneath you taking the weight of your head, your shoulders, your back, your hips, and your legs.
Let this be quieter than a practice and more like company at the end of a long day.
Let the next breath arrive on its own. You are not managing it. You are only meeting it.
You are allowed to be tired without needing to explain why.
Let the body feel heavier in the kindest way, not sinking, only being received.
For now, nothing needs to be changed. Let this moment be exactly as it is, and let that be enough.
Nothing has to become perfect. It only has to become slightly easier than it was a moment ago.
If some feeling is still awake inside you, let it be there without turning it into a problem.
Take one unhurried breath in, and let the exhale be a little longer, as though the body is putting something down.
If the mind is still talking, let it talk farther away. You do not need to answer it.
Picture your thoughts drifting like distant lights seen from far away. They can remain there without reaching you.
You do not have to chase away thought. Simply notice it, and let it pass without following it anywhere.
If it helps, think of the exhale as the part of the breath that knows the way home.
Nothing in you has to be solved before sleep can come closer.
You do not have to stay ahead of the night. You can let the night catch up to you.
You do not need a technique to impress anyone here. A soft breath is enough. A longer exhale is enough.
A restless night can still become a gentle one.
The night does not need anything from you now except your willingness to be carried a little.
Each time the breath leaves, let the shoulders drop by the smallest amount, like a room dimming at night.
Even now, the body may be unwinding in ways you do not have to notice to benefit from.
Sit inwardly with the night the way you might sit beside a quiet window, not asking for anything, only keeping company.
Let the next breath arrive on its own. You are not managing it. You are only meeting it.
You are allowed to be tired without needing to explain why.
It may help to imagine you are floating just below the surface of still water, held quietly from all sides.
Nothing has to become perfect. It only has to become slightly easier than it was a moment ago.
If some feeling is still awake inside you, let it be there without turning it into a problem.
Sometimes the first gift of the night is not sleep itself, but the moment the body stops arguing with wakefulness.
Notice how the body may already be a little farther away from the day than when we began.
You do not need to check whether it is working. Checking wakes the mind back up. Let not knowing be part of the rest.
Take one unhurried breath in, and let the exhale be a little longer, as though the body is putting something down.
If the mind is still talking, let it talk farther away. You do not need to answer it.
It may help to imagine you are floating just below the surface of still water, held quietly from all sides.
Awake or half asleep, you can remain simple here, breathing, resting, letting the mind widen instead of tighten.
If it helps, think of the exhale as the part of the breath that knows the way home.
Nothing in you has to be solved before sleep can come closer.
You do not need a technique to impress anyone here. A soft breath is enough. A longer exhale is enough.
A restless night can still become a gentle one.
Each time the breath leaves, let the shoulders drop by the smallest amount, like a room dimming at night.
Even now, the body may be unwinding in ways you do not have to notice to benefit from.
Let the next breath arrive on its own. You are not managing it. You are only meeting it.
You are allowed to be tired without needing to explain why.
Nothing has to become perfect. It only has to become slightly easier than it was a moment ago.
If some feeling is still awake inside you, let it be there without turning it into a problem.
Sometimes the first gift of the night is not sleep itself, but the moment the body stops arguing with wakefulness.
Let this be one of those quiet moments where nothing is demanded of you.
Now let the breaths become smaller, quieter, almost private.
If you notice my voice fading from your attention, that is a good thing. You can keep drifting.
If sleep is near, let it find you without effort. If you are still awake, keep floating here a little longer in the quiet.
Stay with the softness. Stay with the support beneath you. Let the rest of the night do the rest.